This is a Raspberry Pi 5.
It costs about $100 and it kind of
just looks like a small chunk of
plastic.
But it is a full computer with a
CPU, GPU, RAM, HDMI ports,
USB ports, and we could use
this just as a normal computer or
as a home server to self host web
apps.
We can plug in cameras here and an
AI accelerator chip here and do
some really cool things with
computer vision and these pins let
us control anything in the real
world with code.
So as a programmer you can.
Absolutely anything with this to
get started, we'll need a hard
drive like this SSD, or a cheaper,
easier option is just to use an SD
card.
And although it's not completely
necessary, we'll want an active
cooler so that the pi doesn't get
too hot.
Now this doesn't have an operating
system installed on it yet,
so I'm going to take out the SD
card and plug this into my
computer.
And there's a few Linux
distributions that we can choose
from, but there's also the
official Raspberry Pi OS, which
is a port of Debian.
And we can install the desktop
version and treat this like a
normal desktop or we can install
the lite version and treat it more like a
Linux server and we can set up the
host name and the username right
now so that we can log into the Pi
using SSH.
Then once that's done we can plug
this back into the Raspberry Pi
plug in the Raspberry Pi and then
log into it from my computer using
SSH.
And since this is a new Linux setup
we'll update and upgrade and now I
want to create and host a really
basic web app so I'm going to use a
really basic web framework and then
I can run this and I should be able
to visit this web app on my local.
Network using the Raspberry Pi host
name dot local at port 3000.
So this is a Nextjs app running off
my Raspberry Pi that I can see in
the browser and I can come back in
here and I could start editing
these files with vim.
So I could just delete most of this
boilerplate code and I just put in
a nice little header here and then
this should just update and we
should see this new homepage
running from the Raspberry Pi.
But I would personally much rather
use VS Code.
So I can use the remote SSH extension
and now I'm using VS Code from my
laptop but modifying the code files
on my Raspberry Pi.
And I can install a database on the
Raspberry Pi and code out a full
web app right now, but I'm
just going to display some system
information about the Raspberry Pi.
So I've got some code here that
will tell us the CPU usage,
the temperature, and some of
the other system details just using
the OS and child process library.
And if you want to follow along,
I'll leave a link to all of the
code and
Steps in the description and then
I'm just going to make a new stats
page that will just display that
system information in React
components.
So if I head over to that stats
page, we can now see a bunch
of information about the Raspberry
Pi system, which is kind of
cool, but it's still just running
on my private local network.
And really I want to expose this to
the public Internet.
And there's a few ways we can do
this.
We could set up port forwarding on
our home router and open up our
firewall to let in Https://traffic
from the public Internet, or
we can do something.
A little easier and more secure and
use Cloudflare tunnels where the
Raspberry Pi will tunnel to cloud
flare and then cloud flare handles
all of the traffic over the public
Internet and this service is
completely free.
So I'm going to head over to
Cloudflare Tunnels and then we can
add a tunnel using Cloudflare D
This will be my Pi tunnel.
And since Raspberry Pi OS is just
Debbie and Linux, we can copy
this code snippet into the
Raspberry Pi and when we run this,
it will allow the pi to.
Connect to Cloudflare to tunnel to
Cloudflare.
Then we can set up a domain.
So I already have a domain on
Cloudflare.
I'm going to use that.
I'm going to set the sub domain to
be Rossby and this will be for HTTP
on localhost 3000 since that's
where the NextJs app is running
and I can save that tunnel.
So now from anywhere in the world,
I should be able to go to raspy dot
sam dot
org and see my website and I can go
to that stats page and see all of
the stats from a web app that is
being hosted from my home on a very
cheap computer